<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A goodly dysputacion betwene a christen shomaker, and a popysshe parson with two other parsones more, done within the famous citie of Norembourgh. Translated out of [the] Germayne tongue into Englysshe. By Anthony Scoloker.</title>
            <author>Sachs, Hans, 1494-1576.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21537.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117736</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852946</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852946</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18301</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18301)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 32:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A goodly dysputacion betwene a christen shomaker, and a popysshe parson with two other parsones more, done within the famous citie of Norembourgh. Translated out of [the] Germayne tongue into Englysshe. By Anthony Scoloker.</title>
                  <author>Sachs, Hans, 1494-1576.</author>
                  <author>Scoloker, Anthony, fl. 1548.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Anthony Scoloker. And Wyllyam Seres. Dwellynge wythout Aldersgate.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1548.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum gratia et priuilegio ad imprimandum solum.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 5191.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 5191 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-c.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious disputations --  Germany --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18301:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18301:1"/>
            <p> 
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> A goodly dyſputacion betwene a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten Shomaker / and a Popyſſhe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with two other parſones more, done within the famous Citie of Norembourgh.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Germayne tongue into Englyſſhe. By Anthony Scoloker.</p>
            <p>Imprynted at London by Anthony Scoloker. And Viyllyam Seres. Dwellynge wythout Alderſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate. Anno. 1548.</p>
            <p>¶ Cum Gratia et Priuilegio ad Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18301:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18301:2"/>
            <head>¶ The Shomaker co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the parſones houſe, ſpeaketh to the parſons ſeruaunt.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ood morrow good fellow</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Seruaunt.</speaker>
               <p>ye are welco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maſter Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker</speaker>
               <p>I thanke you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all my hert, Where is your maſter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Seruaunt.</speaker>
               <p>He is in the gallery, O tary a lytle I wyll go and call hym, maſter maſter your ſhomaker is here.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Bene veneritis magiſter Hans.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Deo gratias.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon</speaker>
               <p>What bringe you there / do you brynge my ſlyppers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Yea forſoth Syr, I thoughte you had bene in the Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>No mary. I was yonder behynde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gallery and there haue I mumbled.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>What ſaye you maſter Parſon? haue
<pb facs="tcp:18301:3"/> ye mumbled?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yea I haue ſayd my diuine ſeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> beſydes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at I haue nowe and then fedd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my nyghtyngale.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Syr Iohan I praye you tell me what nyghtingale is it, ſyngeth he yet?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>No forſoth, it draweth to nygh wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker</speaker>
               <p>I knowe a ſhomaker who hath a nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyngale that begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth now fyrſt to ſynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, the deuell of hell take that ſhoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker with all hys nyghtyngales, he hath ſo rayled on oure mooſte holyeſt Father the pope the mooſt hygheſt Father and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend lorde. yea, he hath ſo cryed and called hym abroade, euen as though he had bene the mooſt vyleſt and vngrationſt wretche or knaue of the whole world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>What ſofte and fayre Sir I praie the, he hath partely declared your maner of ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinge, and your diuine ſeruice to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, and nowe I perceaue you do nothing but rayle on hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but what ſhall I
<pb facs="tcp:18301:3"/> ſaie? is your behauiour and lyuinge accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to chriſtes Goſpell / or is it apeſplaye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What the deuell of hell haue theſe dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed ſhomakers to do with oure beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueour and lyuyng?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>It is wryten. When thou ſeeſt thyne <note place="margin">Exod. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Ennemies aſſe fallen vnder hys Burden / thou ſhalt not go by but helpe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp. How muche more is a chriſten Man bounde to helpe hys neyghbour / who he ſeeth lyinge in an heauy conſcience?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>That horeſon aſſched ought not to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue meaned ſpyrituall and relygious men / for they knowe well ynoughe before hand what ſynne is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>But Ezechyell ſpeaketh yf thou ſeeſt <note place="margin">Ezechi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> thy brother ſynne, reprehend hym, or els I wyll require hys bloude, at thy handes Therfore a Chriſten man ought to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend hys brother, be he anoynted or no.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Arte thou a Goſpeller?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Yea forſothe Syr.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:4"/>
               <p> Haſt thow not redde the goſpel of S. Mathew in the vij. Chapter. Thou ſhalte not Iudge to chynte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te thou be not <note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> iudged? But ye Luthery as paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nothyng at all vppon ſuche Sayinges / neyther do ye ſeke for them / for they are playne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>To iudge and reprehend, is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande two maner of wayes, we take not vppon vs to iudge that thynge which only aperteineth to god. As Paule ſayth No man ſhall Iudge the ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, <note place="margin">Roma. 14.</note> but ought, to reprehend and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte hym. As the prophet Eſaye ſaythe Call without Ceaſynge, and exalte youre
<note place="margin">Eſay. 58.</note> voice lyke a trompett to declare my people theyr offenſes. et cetera.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Ther is alſo written. Thou ſhalte not make the chefeſt of the people aſhamed.
<note place="margin">Exod. 22.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Who is the chefeſte, amonge the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple / is it not the Emperour, kynges / pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Dukes / Earles, with theyr knygtes eſquires and worldly power?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, nay. The pope is Chriſtes vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and next vnder hym, Cardynals, Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb facs="tcp:18301:4"/> with all the ſpiritualte / as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten. Solite de maioritate et obediencia. Theſe ſpirytuall men repreſent the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and the worldly powers repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t only the moone. Wherout doth folowe that the pope muſt nedes be of greater power then the Emperour, who is faine to kyſſe hys fete.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Is the pope ſuch a puyſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lorde? tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Iohan. 18.</note> then is he not Chriſtes vicare. For Chriſt ſayth, my kyngdome is not of thys worlde. And Iohn. 6. Chriſt (when he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we <note place="margin">Iohan. 6.</note> that men wolde make hym kyng) we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<note place="margin">Luke. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> hys wayes. Chriſt alſo ſayd vnto hys dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciples. Worldely prynces haue dominion and beare Rule, and the Myghtyr of the earthe are called Lordes / but let it not be ſo amonge you. For who of you wyll be the greateſt ſhalbe the leaſte, and the che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt as a Seruaunt, and therfore the pope and ye ſpyrytuall men are but mynyſters vnto the Chriſtians (in caſe ye be of God) and therfore menne may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ehende you well Inoughe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>The pope with hys, is nor bounde to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beye the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God. As it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſpirituall lawe. C. Solite de maioritate et obediencia out of the whych
<pb facs="tcp:18301:5"/> we do conclude that the pope is no ſinnes but the moſt holyeſt and in all thyng inre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehenſible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>It is wrytten, who ſo ever ſayth that he is wythout ſynne, is a lyer, oute of the
<note place="margin">Iohan. 1.</note> whiche followeth that the Pope muſte nedes be a ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner or a lier (if he be not both) and not the moſt holyeſt / but is greatly to be reprehended.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What I ſay / although the pope wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo wycked, that he dyd bryng a great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tytude of people into hell, yet may no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reprehende him. For it is wrytten in oure lawes dyſt. xi. Sipapa. Howe doth that <note place="margin">diſtinct. 40</note> pleaſe the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>It is written in the goſpell of Math. <note place="margin">Math. 18.</note> if thy brother do ſynne reprehend him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene hym and the / and if he heare the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then haſt thou wonne him. Doth the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe vſe ſuch Godly acres?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Doeſt thou call this to reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a brotherly ſorte, to cry and call it out ſo openly?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>It is further written in the ſame text,
<pb facs="tcp:18301:5"/> in caſe thy brother heare the not / then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke one or two wyth you / and if he heare you not then, then tell it to the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, and let him go lyke a heathen and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fidell, euen as thou art ſir domine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>I praye the what preuayleth it that thou doeſt call vs thus a broad lyke gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppers, conſyderyng we paſſe nothyng for it. For we holde vs by our decrees?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Therfore ſayth Chryſt, in caſe men do not heare you, then ſhake the duſt from your fete for a wytnes that the Kyngdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of God hath bene nygh vnto them. For theyr Iudgement ſhall be greater at the day of dome, then to Sodoma a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morra. In what caſe ſhalt thou be then; ſeing thou wylt not be reprehended?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>I wolde graunte it to be ſo / in caſe they were learned men, but it becommeth not the laye people to reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ſpiritualte</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>An aſſe reprehended Balaain the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet. Wherfore then is it not lawfull. For a lay man to reprehende a ſpirituall man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhomaker ought to meddle with grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing
<pb facs="tcp:18301:6"/> of his lether and clouting of his ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, and not with holy ſcripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Howe can ye proue that by ſcripture / that a Chriſten man may not rede, wryte and ſearch in the ſcriptures? For Chryſte ſayth, ſearch the Scriptures for ſhe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth witnes of me. And the pſalmograph ſayth alſo. Bleſſed is the man that ſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyeth nyght and daye in the lawes of the lord, And Peter ſayth alſo Prepare your <note place="margin">1. Petri. 3.</note> ſelues to anſwere euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / the grounde requyreth the hope whiche is in you, and in lyke maner Paule teacheth the Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to fyght agaynſt the aſſaultes of the deuell, with the ſwerde of Gods woorde. <note place="margin">Epheſi. 6.</note> Oh lord howe were it poſſyble for vs to reſyſt, if we knewe nothing of the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Euen lyke a heape of giſe in the water.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Mocke at your pleaſure. The Iewes knowe theyr lawe by roote or wythoute the boke, ſhal not we that are Chriſtians know the goſpell of Ieſus Chryſt? whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the power of God to as manye as ſhalbe ſaued / as Paule ſayth. <note place="margin">1. Corin. 1.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, thou ſhalt know it as Chriſt hath
<pb facs="tcp:18301:6"/> tolde. The ſcribes and pharizees haue ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Moſes ſeat. What ſo euer they <note place="margin">Math. 22.</note> teach you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oke you do the ſame which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth the dayly preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / doth not this ſuffiſe the laye people?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Ther is alſo written in the ſame chap. They laye heauy a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnbearable burdens vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mennes neckes, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſuch ſygnifye the tradicions and commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of men wherby ye dryue and oppreſſe vs laye peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, bryngyng vs in heauy conſciens / wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſhulde we then folowe you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>How ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt thou proue that by ſcripture?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chryſt ſayth in the be fore named chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Wo be vnto you ye hipocrites a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizees, that ſhut vp the kyngdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for the people / thou wylte not entre into it thy ſelfe, nor yet ſuffre any other to enter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yea that was ſpoken to the prieſtes of the Iewes, and not to our prieſts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Mary. Syr ye haue fyrſt taken the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of pharizees vppon you Which ſytte vppon moſes ſeate etc. Although it be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:18301:7"/> of the Prieſtes of the Iewes (as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ueth is) euen ſo it alſo ſpoken of you. For your workes beare witnes / thou ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the widdowes houſes / as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> text fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth declare, in good fayth ſix domine you haue taken your ſelfe by the noſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Fye on the. Howe do theſe horeſon lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therians reioyce and laughe in their fyſt, when they can fynde ſome ſayings out of the ſcripture / they trouble and vexe one therwith, without ceaſyng.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Syr I pray the be not diſcontented fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in good fayth I ſpeake of a good zeale.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>I am not angry, but I am bounde to tell it the, it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not the laye People to meddle with the ſcripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chryſt ſayth. Beware of falſe prophetes <note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> and Paule to the Philippi. iij. take hede. <note place="margin">Philipi. 3.</note> If we myght not be ſuffered to rede the ſcriptures, how ſhulde we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> know theſe thynges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>The ſame apperteyneth to the papiſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry as Paule ſayth to Timoth. 1. ye ſhall correct the ſeducers with all extremitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:7"/>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Yea they do it not, but do manifeſtly agaynſt it as it daylie doth apere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon</speaker>
               <p>Let them care for that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>No ſyr not ſo / we wyll not eſteme it ſo lyght / it they wyll not, then muſte we take hede that we folow not them / for no man ſhall beare an others burden.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Saye what ye lyſt, it apperteyneth not to the laye people to meddel with the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture as Paule ſaythe. 1. Cor. 7. Let euery <note place="margin">1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> man walke accordynge to the lordes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng. Howe ſayeſt thou nowe? thou wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt haue ſcripture, and now I haue ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tured the I trow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker</speaker>
               <p>Yea paule ſpeaketh that of the outward conuerſacion and lyuinge, of boundemen and Fremen / as in the ſame Chapter it is clearley ſpecifyed. But here doth he forbid no man to ſearche the worde of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Doeſt thou not here? ye mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſte fyrſte be called throughe the holy oyntment / and after that / be choſen of the higher powers other wyſe is it not laufull for any man to meddell with the ſcrypture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:8"/>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chryſt ſayth. The harueſt is great, but <note place="margin">Luke. 10.</note> ther are very fewe labourers, pray to the lorde of the harueſt to ſend labourers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his harueſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erby the callyng muſte nedes be inwardlye of God / and not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardely. For outwardly are all prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers called, as well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſe as the true.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſh. It is but folyſhnes to reaſon with ſuch pratlers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker</speaker>
               <p>It is euen ſo with you, as it was with <note place="margin">Luke. 9.</note> the diſcyples / whiche were offended that othermen caſtoute deuelles in Chryſtes name, as wel as they. But Chriſt ſayd for bydde them not. For who ſoeuer is not a gaynſte you is with you. And if ye were true Chryſtyans / ye ſhulde euen reioyce that the lay people do vnderſtand &amp; know the worde of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What grefe is it to you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sho.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe we haue forſaken the deuell in our baptym, therfore are we thus dily<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent to fyght with Gods worde agaynſt him &amp; his kingdom, yea and to auenture and Ieoparde both body and goods.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>It were better for ye lay people to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy howe to get the lyuing of your wyues and chyldren,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sho.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:8"/>
               <p> Chryſt forbiddeth and ſayth, take no thought what ye ſhall eate and drinke or
<note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> what clothes ye ſhal put on, for ſuche thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges do the heathen ſeke, but ſeke fyrſt the kingdom of God. &amp;c. And it ſhalbe geuen you aboundauntly. The man lyueth not onely by breade, but of euery word w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> procedeth out of the mouth of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Satiſfye and content your ſelfe ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with / and bake neuer a whitte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>We muſt labour, as it was commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <note place="margin">Gene. 3. &amp; Iob. 5.</note> to Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are borne to labour lyke the byrdes to flye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Where ſhuld you and other laye people haue learned it? ſome of them knowe ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther A nor B.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chryſt ſayth. They ſhal all be taught of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>But there nedeth alſo learni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, wherfore are the vniuerſities els ordeyned?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>In what vniuerſitie (I pray the) dyd Ioan ſtudye? Who wrote ſo profoundly In the beginning was the worde and the
<pb facs="tcp:18301:9"/> worde was God. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ete. For he was bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a fyſſher as it is wrytten.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What man / he was illuminate wyth the holy goſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>It is wrytten. And it ſhall happen in the later daies, ſayth God, I wyl power out my ſpyrite vppon all fleſhe. What meane ye? thynke ye that thys is not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of vs?
<note place="margin">Actes. 2.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>No, it is ſpoken of the Apoſtles, as peter witneſſeth. Therfor hold thy peace and ſpeake no more of the ſpyrite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chryſte ſayth who ſo beleueth on me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out of his bodye ſhall flowe ſtreames of
<note place="margin">Iohan. 7.</note> lyuing water. Whych is expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned by the Euangeliſt, that he ſpeaketh the ſame of the holygoſt whych all they ſhuld receyue that beleue in him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What I ſaye my thynke that thou ſmelleſt after Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuanus that heretyke / wyth thy holyghoſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Paule ſpeaketh. Do ye not knowe <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. 3.</note> that ye are the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of God; and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte of God dwelleth in you? And to the
<pb facs="tcp:18301:9"/> Gallath. 4. Seynge ye are nowe become chyldren, God hathe ſente his ſpirite in to
<note place="margin">Gallat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> your hartes, who calleth. Abba, that is, be loued father. He maketh vs ryghtuous accordyng to his mercy, through the bath of renouacion / and the renewyng of the holyghoſt / whiche he hath powred habou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dauntly <note place="margin">Timo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4.</note> in vs. And to the Romaynes in the. 5. chapter. As the ſpirite nowe dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <note place="margin">Roman. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> in you, who hath rayſed Ieſus Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte from death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>I fynde no holy ſpirite in me, you nor I are not noble inough therto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Wherfore are ye then called ſpiritual ſeyng you haue not the ſpyrite of God? ye ought with good right to be called ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eleaſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>They be other maner of people then ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you or I am whiche haue the ſpiryte of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ought not to haue reſpect vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For God is no accepter of parſons. It is
<note place="margin">Actes. 10.</note> alſo written. The ſpirite of God ſhal reſt
<note place="margin">Eſay. 66.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon a broken or weake harte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:10"/>
               <p> ſhewe me one, I praye th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Paull ſpeaketh openly. Who ſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. hath not the ſpyrite of Chryſt, perteyneth
<note place="margin">Rom. an 8.</note> not to hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Oh / trulye it is a very poore and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſpirit / which ye Lutherians haue, I thinke he is as blacke as a cole. I praye the tell me what make ye wyth your holy ghoſt? I beleue verely that he ſlepeth both nyght and daye by you, for men can not ſo much as ones ſpye hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt ſayth, Geue not that whych is <note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> holy to dogges, neyther caſt ye your pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les before ſwyne, leaſte they treade them vnder theyr fete.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What, are ye not aſhamed to ſpeake ſuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Rude and Vncommelye woordes before me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>I pray the ſir domine be not diſpleaſed for it is the ſaying of holy ſcripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>yea, yea, yea, ye Lutherians ſpeake much, of Goddes woorde, and it waxeth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger the worſe / I can not ſpye any amende<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:18301:10"/> in none of you all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt ſay the Luk. 19. The kyngdome of God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not outwardly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or wyth
<note place="margin">Luke. 19.</note> lokyng vp / that men myght poynt it wyth fyngers, to ſale here in thys or in that pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce is it / but it is inwardly in you. that is, it ſtandeth not in outwarde workes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Men may perceaue that by your deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſeruyce. Ye praye not, nether go ye to the Churche nor to the dayly ſeruice, nor in a maner to nothynge at all that good is Is then ſuche kyngdom Gods kyngdom, amongeſt you Lutherians? I beleue it is the great deuell of helles kyngdome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt ſpeaketh, The tyme ſhall come / <note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and is euen nowe, that men ſhall praye no more vpon this mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain nor at Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſhall praye only in ſpyryte and veryte Thys caſteth downe and condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neth your daylye ſeruice with alſo your num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred prayers. For Chryſte wholy and all abhorreth youre nombred prayers wyth youre outward mumblyng. Where as he ſaythe Math. xv. Thys people worſhyp <note place="margin">Math. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e wyth theyr lyppes, but theyr harte is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re from me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:11"/>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>And Chriſt ſayth, ye ſhall praye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note place="margin">Luke. 18.</note> ceaſyng.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>yea, he meaneth, to praye without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge in the ſpyrite, but Chryſt diſpyſeth your prayer: ſaying, ye ſhall not make ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny wordes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Gentle frende what is that for a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> to praye in ſpirite and veritie? teache me that ſame I praye the, then ſhall I nede no more to ſay my matte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nor myne other ſeruice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Reade that lytle boke of Marten Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, intituled of the Chriſten lybertye w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> he dedicated to Pope Leo, and there ſhall ye fynde it brefely declared.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>I wolde rather that Luther wyth al hys bokes were burnt, I neuer in all my lyfe dyd reade none of them, nor yet wyll as I am aduyſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>What, why doeſt thou iudge then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Mary becauſe he worſhippeth not the ſaintes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:11"/>
               <p> Chryſt ſayth. Thou ſhalt onely wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyp thy lorde God, and ſerue him onelye. <note place="margin">Math. 4.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, we muſt haue interceſſours to god</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Iohn ſayth, If any man haue ſynned we haue a mediatour by God / whiche is <note place="margin">1. Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Ieſus Chryſt, who is ryghtuous, who is alſo the peacemaker for oure ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yea thou ſpeakeſt fayre wordes good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, but nede compelleth a man to begge yf thy legge were broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / woldeſt thou not go to ſaint Wolfgange? or if thou haddeſt the tothache woldeſt thou not pray to ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Apoſonia?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>No trulye. Chryſt ſayth, come vnto me al <note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> ye that labour and are laden, and I wyll caſe you. Where then wyll we ſeke better helpe, ye haue made Idoles of the ſaintes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo ye haue ſeduced and brought vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chryſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, I haue hearde wel Inough of you Lutheria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that ye do neuer faſt / doth Lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers holy ghoſt teache you that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>We are not commaunded of God to
<pb facs="tcp:18301:12"/> faſt, but God hath lefte it free. Chryſt ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th when thou wylt faſte, annoint thy head <note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> and waſſhe thy Face, he ſayth not, thowe ſhalt or tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt faſte, lyke our Romyſh ſtepfather doth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, but ye neuer do faſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker</speaker>
               <p>I beleue that he handycraftes menne do faſte better (yea although they eate. 4. tymes in a daye) then all the pryeſtes and ſhauelyngs of the realme. It is manyfeſte Inough. I nede not to ſpeake any more therof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Holde thy peace then, and let me ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, as concernyng faſtinge that is the leaſt faute, but ye Lutherians eate fletſhe on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fryday, that the deuell of hell mought blyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>It is not forbydden of God to eate fleſh, and therfore is it not ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne / ſo farre fourth as the weake people are not therby offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. <note place="margin">Math. 15.</note> Chryſt ſaith. That which goeth into the Mouthe, defyleth not the Manne / but that which commeth oute of the mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th defyleth the Manne / as whooredome, murther, aduoutye, theft, falſe wytneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:18301:12"/> bearing, bacbyting. &amp;c. And Paule: 1 Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthi. What ſoeuer is ſold in the market <note place="margin">1. Corinth.</note> that eate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>yea, ſaye what ye lyſt, but good olde cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtomes whych haue bene kept and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued aboue foure hondreth yeres / are not to be deſpyſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chryſt ſayth Iohn in. 14. I am the <note place="margin">Iohan. 14.</note> waye, verytie / and the euerlaſtynge Lyfe / but he ſaith not I am the cuſtom. Their fore muſt we ſticke and cleaue to the very<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie whyche is Gods worde, and euen god hym ſelfe, which endureth for euer more
/ But cuſtome commeth of men, whyche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re <note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> all lyers / as the. 115. pſal. ſaieth, which <note place="margin">Pſalm. 115</note> ſayinge dothe whole and all ouerthrowe your cuſtomes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Syr I pray the tell me, the Lutherians do neuer ſhryue nor confeſſe them, whych is the greateſt hereſie of all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Nether is that commanded of God, nor yet pronounced, nether in the olde nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the newe Teſtament.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Dyd not Chryſt ſaye Go and ſhewe thy <note place="margin">Math, 22.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18301:13"/> ſelfe vnto the prieſtes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Doeſt thou call ſhewing ſhryuing, that is a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders ſtraunge Englyſſhe, ye muſt declare it better vnto me by ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. If the ſame ſhryuing in the eare were ſuch a great bonde a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d holy thyng, it ſhuld truely be clerer declared in the ſcripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What I ſay / wyll ye do nothyng els but that whyche is commaunded yow of GOD in the ſcripture? that is a pitious caſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>I can not fulfyll the ſame, as it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared <note place="margin">Actes. 15.</note> / what nede I to lay any more bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vpon me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Such thynges haue the holy fathers ordeyned in their councels.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Who gaue them Auctoritie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Chryſt ſayth I haue yet many thyngs to ſay vnto you, but ye can not beare it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wey
<note place="margin">Iohan. 16.</note> now: Howe ſayſt thou? Are not than the councels inſtituted of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>But Chryſt ſpeaketh before that, I ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:18301:13"/> ſend the comforter (which is the ſpyrite of trueth which procedeth of the father) and <note place="margin">Iohan. 15.</note> he ſhall declare you all thynges whiche I haue tolde you. Marke, he ſayth not, he ſhall teache you new thinges, whych I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue not tolde you, but the ſame thynges w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> I haue tolde you, euen the ſame ſhall he de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare vnto you: And ſayth further hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / he ſhal leade you in all treuth</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Thus holdeſt thou nothynge of the councels I perceaue well Inough.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>yes verelye of that counſell whych the Apoſtles kepte at Ieruſalem.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Haue the apoſtles alſo kept a counſell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>yea if you haue a byble.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>yea I haue one, O Katherin / brynge he ther that ſame great old boke <note place="margin">Katherin the parſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s handmayd</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Katherin.</speaker>
               <p>Syr is that ſame it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What no / that ſame is the decrees, loke ye make it not ſoule. <note place="margin">what elſes.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Katheryn.</speaker>
               <p>Syr is thys it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:14"/>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, make it cleane, and ſwepe of the <note place="margin">So much dyd he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde the byble.</note> duſt and cobwebbes now maſter ſhoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker where is it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Seke in the Actes of the Apoſtles in <note place="margin">Actes. 13.</note> the. 15. chapter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Seke your ſelf / I am not much vſed <note place="margin">Now he telleth truth.</note> in the ſame boke I knowe other thynges w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> are proffytabler vnto me, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>There it is / beholde Syr.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Katherin, rede Actum 15. nay let alone, I wyll rede it my ſelf, and I wyll know what the ſame olde fellowes haue made.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, Rede, and ye ſhall fynde that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not ſay the burdens of the olde Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament vppon the Chriſtians, therfore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re we not bounde to heare you in the olde, muche leſſe in the new teſtament.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>But Chriſt ſayth. Whoſoeuer heareth <note place="margin">Luke. 10.</note> you, heareth me, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d he that deſpyſeth you, deſpyſeth me, is that ſame not cleare In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ough?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:14"/>
               <p> Yea, when you do ſyncerlye and pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye teach Gods worde, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are men bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to heare you euen as Chryſte hym ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye preach youre owne Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginacyons and inuencyons, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought no man to gyue care vnto you. For all that is not planted of God my heauenly father ſhalbe plucked vp by the rotes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Are the councelles then alſo the lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng of men?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>If a man ſhulde ſay the trueth, the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celles haue done great dammage in Chry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hendome by two maner of wayes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What hurt or dammage? declare them I pray the hartelye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Syomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Fyrſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes which are innumerable and vnmeaſurable as you your ſelf knowe / and that which is worſt of all haue bene by exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munycacyons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmed, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d aboue that mooſt part are not grounded in the ſcrypture, and ſuch your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts men haue highly eſtemed and therwith greatly charged mens co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ences / and haue bene reputed lyke the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundmentes of God / yea, ſet before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18301:15"/> wherby the commaundementes of God haue bene ſet backe and made vnknowen to the people. Such people hath Paul de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clared with their commaundementes.</p>
               <p>That in the latter tymes ſhulde departe <note place="margin">1. Timo. 4</note> from the fayth, and gyue hede vnto ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of errour / and deuelyſhe doctryne of them which ſpeake falſe thorow ypocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy &amp; haue their conſciences marked with an hote yron, forbyddyng to marry, and commaundyng to abſteyne from meates which God hathe created to be receyued wyth thankes geuyng of them which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue and know the truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>How is that come to paſſe, with what commaundementes I pray the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>To eate fleſh on the fryday, hath bene taken for a greater ſynne, then to kepe a whore or two.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>I vnderſtande you very well, what dammages are there more?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Secondarely they haue brought forth many ſtraunge Gods ſeruiſes / and called them good workes, which is nothyng el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les (if a man ſhulde ſaye ſo the) but verye
<pb facs="tcp:18301:15"/> apeſplay and outward folyſſhnes / Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of God neuer ſpake one worde / wherby both we and they / haue neglected, and not regarded the good woorkes whych God hath commaunded vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>what are then the ryght true workes of a chryſten man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chryſt ſayth. All what thou woldeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> men ſhuld do to the, do euen the ſame vnto them / and that is the fulfilling of the who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le lawe and prophetes. And he doth teache <note place="margin">Math. 15.</note> vs to fede the hungry / to geue drinke to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrſtye / to harbarrowe the harbarroules to clothe the naked, to viſite the ſycke, and to comforte the priſonner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Are that only the workes of a Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, and the wholl ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of a Chryſten ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Yea / a true and faythfull chryſten man <note place="margin">Iohan. 3.</note> which is borne a newe out of the water a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the Spyrite (as it is written Iohan. iij. chapter) ſerueth God onely in ſpyrite and Veritie, and ſerueth alſo his Neighbour, wyth the woorkes of charitie / that is the whole ſumme of a Chriſten lyfe / but theſe
<pb facs="tcp:18301:16"/> papiſtes meane that ſuch a Chryſten lyfe is nothing at all, becauſe the ſame workes haue not ſuch an outwarde ſhyne as their workes do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Thynke ye then that our ſyngyng and Readyng is of no worth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chryſte ſhall require nothyng elles of <note place="margin">Math. 15.</note> vs at the day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / then the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes <note place="margin">Gene. 3. &amp;</note> of mercy / then ſhal ye prieſtes and mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes <note place="margin">Iob. 5.</note> ſtande lyke foles which haue left their eares at the pylory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it wonders well / gette you to the furnace and warme you a lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell,
<note place="margin">Luke. 10.</note> doth Luther teache you ſuche thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>No.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What holdeſt thou of Luther? I pray the tell me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>I hold him for a Chryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Doctour a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d I thynk there hath not bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a better ſens the Apoſtles tyme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What proffyt hath he done in the chriſten fayth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:16"/>
               <p> Mary, fyrſt, he hathe diſcouered and brought to lyght youre falſe doctryne, com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes, tradicions and Imagy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyons, and admonyſſhed and warned vs therof. Secondarely / he hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs by ſcripture / that we ſhulde confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe that we are all the bondmen of ſynne. Thyrdely / that Chryſt alone is our ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and redemer, of which two points the <note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> whole ſcripture is full, wherby we learne
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> to putt oure truſte / hope and ſayth onelye in Chriſte, which is a true and godly wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke to ſaluacion, as Chriſt ſayth Ioan. 6 And Chriſt ſayth. Mat. 5. Let your lyght <note place="margin">Iohan. 11.</note> braſte oute / and ſo ſhyne before the people / <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> that they (ſeing your good workes) maye praiſe the father which is in heauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Nedeth no worke therto?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Paule ſayth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ad Rom. 5. we hold it ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, <note place="margin">Roma. 5.</note> that man is onelye made right wes through fayth, without the workes, &amp; to the Romaynes in the laſt chapter. The <note place="margin">Rom. vlt.</note> tyghtuous ſhall lyue by fayth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Iames ſayth in his. 2. chap. Fayth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out <note place="margin">Iacob. 2</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood workes is dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:17"/>
               <p> A true Chriſten fayth can neuer be I<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dell but bryngeth alwayes good workes and frutes forth. For Chryſt ſayth / A good tree an brynge forth no euell frute, <note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> but ſuch good workes ought not to be do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne for to meryte or deſerue heauen ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by / for Chryſt hath merited and deſerued it for vs, neyther for feare, and to a voyde the paynes of hell, for Chryſt hath dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueryd vs therof, neyther for honour, for all honour ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lbe geuen onely vnto God, as it is writen. But ye ſhall do them for
<note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> loue, for a thankes geuyng to God, and to the helpe and profyt of your neyghbour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>If Luther be ſo ryghtuous and ſo good a doctour as you name hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be, how cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it then that ſo fewe greate lords do cleaue and ſtyck vnto his doctryne: Saue onely a heape of rude and vnlearned peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Pylate, Herode, Cayphas nor Annas, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leued not to Chryſt nor yet the pharize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, but the common people. Therfore Chriſt reioyced in ſpirite, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſayd. Father I thanke you, that ye haue hydden the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe <note place="margin">Luke. 10.</note> thynges from the wyſe of the world, &amp; haue opened it to the lytle flocke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:17"/>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What I ſaye the common people clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne leaſt of all to Luther and hys doctrine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Your dulheaded and folyſhe preachers are cauſe of that / whych without any ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, crye and call, he is an heretyke / he is an heretike. But Chryſte hath declared
<note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> to the litell flocke. Go thoroughe the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe gate, for the gate is wyde and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way is broade whyche leadeth to dampnation, and ther are many which walke in it, And ther are many called and fewe electe. <note place="margin">Math. 22.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Men do vſe to ſpeake ſuche wordes in tauernes, vpon the market, and elles wher lyke fooles, whych ought not to be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſuche places.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt ſayeth / what I ſaye to you in ſecret, that ſhall ye preache vppon the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe
<note place="margin">Math. 10:</note> toppes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>If I ſhulde ſaye trueth. I holde Lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther for the greateſte heretyke, that euer was ſence Arrius Tyme, and thou arte hys folower, and ther is no good in you, nether commeth theyr any good fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you / vnderſtandeſte thou that? The ſame ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell
<pb facs="tcp:18301:18"/> do I gyue both to Luther and to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Veryly you haue hitte the prycke / fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theyr is no man good but God only. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> oure nature is whole and all corrupte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 14.</note> vs, as it is wrytten. Geneſ. 8. The hart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of man is inclyned to euell / euen from hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Gene. 8.</note> youthe / whych dayly muſte be mortifyed wyth the croſſe, leaſte it myght hinder th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpirite. For nature ceaſeth not to ſeke that thynge wherunto it is inclined, all though the ſpyryte be made ryghtuous through<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fayth. For it is wrytten Prouer. 24.</p>
               <p>The ryghtuous falleth ſeuen tymes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the daye. Therfore do we daily praye. For<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giue
<note place="margin">Prou. 24.</note> vs our treſpaces Math. 6. and paule to the Rom. 7. The good which I wolde <note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> I do not / and the euell whiche I hate, I
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> do, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d after that ſpeaketh he. O miſerable man / who ſhall delyuer me from the body of death? Therwyth declareth he that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are ſynners euen vnto death. But ſyr Do ruine / yf thou arte wyth out Synne, caſte the fyrſt ſtone vppon vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Ye are all vn proffitable people, ye can prate very well / I truſte ye ſhal ſhortly be
<note place="margin">Iohan. 8.</note> knocked vppon your boanes, for I percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue there is none other remedye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:18"/>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>What wolde you be in hande with the ſwerde? that apperteyneth not to the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon</speaker>
               <p>Hath not Chriſt Luce. 22. ordeyned two ſwerdes, one ſpirituall and an other temporall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chryſt did forbydde Peter. Math. 26 and ſayd he that ſtriketh with the ſwerd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> ſhall peryſh with the ſwerde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>It helpeth not by other meanes, therfore muſt it be holpen / wyth a quicke puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for hereſy hath in a maner taken y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpperhande, therfore it is hygh tyme to ſtryke in the flocke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, do not ſo, but rather follow the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell of Gamaliel / Actum in the 5. chapter. If the ddctryne be of God, ye can not for <note place="margin">Actes. 5.</note> bydde nor defend it, and if it be of menne, then ſhall it fall without any ſwerde / to the intent ye he not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as one that wyll fyght agaynſt God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Ther ſhall come nothyng elles therof for this ſhalbe the ende.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:19"/>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe, O lord of heauen, thy wyll be fulfylled. Math 6. The Diſcyple is not aboue hys maſter. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> perſecuted <note place="margin">Iohan. 15.</note> me. they ſhal perſecute you alſo
/ a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppy <note place="margin">Luke. 6.</note> are ys, when ye are hated / dyſdayned and diſpyſed for my names ſake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Some ſhall then holde their peace, whych nowe do call and roare a lowde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>He that confeſſeth me before the world him wyll I knowledge and confeſſe befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re my heauenly father.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ſhall be handeled and ſerued lyke as heretikes ought to be ſerued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Chryſt ſayth feare not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whych may <note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> deſtroy the body only, but feare him which may deſtroy both body and ſoule. O lorde God, howe good is it to dye for thy names ſake?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>It were euen your iuſt rewarde / an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyke (after the third admonicion and war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning) ought to be put to death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>But yow ought fyrſte to proue or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyne
<pb facs="tcp:18301:19"/> vs to be heretikes, wyth the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>That may we full eaſely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Then ſhall God require our bloude at youre hands / becauſe you haue ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs, and the pore ſhepe of Chryſt to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue bene thus long ſeduced and ledde out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the right way. And that you haue not reſyſted and diſputed with ſo many prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of this learning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>It ſhal ſhortly come to paſſe, we haue taken our aduiſe and counſell vppon the matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, is that true indede? I perceaue ye do fulfyll the ſayeng of Mat. And the Phariz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es went and helde a councel how <note place="margin">Math. 22.</note> they might trippe him in his wordes, and dyd ſend officers vnto him / with the offy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cers of Herode.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What elles? Thus ought the herety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to be ſerued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, lorde. Theſe true preachers wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de fayne bryng vs all to Chryſte, no man
<pb facs="tcp:18301:20"/> excepted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And thow woldeſte bringe both vs and thy ſelfe to the deuell. Thou wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt fayne that the Fyre of Heauen ſhulde fall on vs Luk. 9. Heare what Chryſt fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth.
<note place="margin">Luke. 9.</note> Do ye not knowe what chylderen of ſpyrite ye are? The ſonne of man is not co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me to deſtroy the ſoules of men, but to ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue them. 2. Cori. 13. He hath geuen me po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer (ſaith he) not to deſtroy, but to ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. <note place="margin">2. Cori. 13.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>What, I ſay, I wyll euen the ſame alſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Fyre and ſwerde ſerueth not therto, but the woorde of God Hebr. 4. Which is
<note place="margin">Hebre. 4.</note> ſherper then a two edged ſworde. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if thou arte of God, defende thy doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and lawes with Gods word, which <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> is the power of God. 1. Corinthi. 1.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>All thys helpeth you neuer a whytte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Ye bringe not Gods worde / ye ſeke not the honour of God, but your owne power honour, and Ryches, againſt whyche the worde of God ſpeaketh, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d therfore do ye perſecute it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, thou prateſt nothing elles, but to here a manne, when the harte is full, then
<pb facs="tcp:18301:20"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nneth the mouthe ouer. Luke. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>I maye well lyken you / lyke as Chriſt lykeneth the chylderen ſyttyng in the mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kett place
/ criyng one to an other and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. We haue pypes vnto you and ye haue <note place="margin">Luk. 7.</note> not daunſed. We haue mourned to you &amp; ye haue not wepte. Euen ſo is it with you, If a man ſpeake vnto you confortablye of the worde of God, then do ye deryde it. If a man do tell it you earneſtlye / then are ye angry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Although thow dyddeſt ſynge lyke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Larke / thowe ſhalt not make me other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe then I am.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Youre harte is waxen harde and ſtony as kyng Pharao, Exodi. Rede from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. 7. Chapter to the. 15. who n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther regar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded no wonder nor places. etc.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haddeſt almoſt hit the prycke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Me thynketh that thou arte lyke the falſe off yeer Luk. 6. What ſhall I do? the lorde wyll take the offyce from me, I can not dygge, and I am a ſhamed to begge. Euen that ſame feare ye ſpyrituall menne
<pb facs="tcp:18301:21"/> alſo no exhortacion nor admoniſhing can helpe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>No man commeth to me vnleſſe my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther drawe him, wyll you then conuert a man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Oh ſyr I loue to heare the ſame wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des with all my harte. It is written Iob 15. without me canſt thou do nothing / and further thou haſte not choſen me, but I haue choſe the, therfore lyeth it not in our power, but it is God which muſt conuert vs. Which I do wyſſhe you all from the botome of my harte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>When do they ryng in the church Ka<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therin giue me my ſirplys and tippet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Katherin.</speaker>
               <p>Well beloued maſter / go in peaſe, I hope all thinges ſhalbe well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>With the helpe of God, now peace be with you, beloued ſyr take no diſpleaſure wyth me, but pardon me if I haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>God pardon and forgyue vs all our ſynnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ſhomaker.</speaker>
               <p>Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:21"/>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Beholde how quicke theſe lay men are in tellyng of their tale to vs which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>noynted. I thynke that the deuel of hell be patched and clouted in the ſho. Skynne, he hath ſo ſtricken me vpon my breſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e / that if. I had not bene ſo depely lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he ſhuld haue made me a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſſe, therfor he ſhall make no more ſhoes for me / but Hans zobell ſhall be my ſhomaker, for he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a very ſymple man, and one that dothe not much reaſon of the ſcrypture
/ nor of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Lutheryans hereſy, which appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not to the laye people, nether becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it them to dyſpute with their ſoule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kepers, for Salomon ſayth who ſoeuer walketh ſymply, walketh well. Ah, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſaying ought I to haue layde to that dulheaded ſhomaker, peraduenture, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>huld haue had nothyng to ſay thervpon / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut haue bene ſtarke dome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Katherin</speaker>
               <p>Ah maſter, I feared greatly (when I ſawe you coud not ouercome hym wyth ſcripture) that you ſhuld haue ſtrycken hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon his pate with the ſlyppers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>If I had not feared that an oproare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nyght haue ryſen among the comens / I
<pb facs="tcp:18301:22"/> ſhuld verely haue layd the ſlippers in his face, ſo that neyther Paule no nor Chriſt hym ſelfe ſhuld haue ſwepte it from him in thre daies, for all that he truſteth ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che in them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Katheryn.</speaker>
               <p>I maruell greatly how it commeth that the ſay people are ſo learned.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>If thou wilt know it, I ſhall tell i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the. The cauſe is that the ſpiritualty is no more regarded. Here afore times did oure holy father the pope of Rome wyth his by<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhops forbydde ſuch heretikes as Luther is, according to the ſpirituall lawe and compelled them to recant, lyke Ioan hus was ſerued at conſtance. If men dyd now compell theſe preachers of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to holde theyr Peace, then ſhulde i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be as good as euer it was, and then ſhulde the ſpiritualty be honoured, but when we go aboute to cauſe them to holde their pea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, then wyl they inmediatly dyſpute with the pope and Byſſhops, whiche is a thing that neuer was hearde in the worlde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that ſuch vyle parſonnes ſhulde dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with the mooſt holyeſt father whiche are not worthy to ſpeke to his holmes, but it ſhall ſhortly take an ende. Although theſe preachers wyll not holde their pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,
<pb facs="tcp:18301:22"/> they ſhall be compelled to holde theyre peace, for all that they lay Saynes Paul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les wryting before them / and though they had Paules ſwerde alſo, yet muſte they lye doune and not ſo much as ones kycke, when it pleaſeth ones the Holye Father of Rome, then muſt the laye people hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de theyr peace alſo, and then ſhall we come to oure former worthynes and pryſtyne honour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Katheryn.</speaker>
               <p>Verily Syr It were very good, for every man diſpiſeth a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mocketh with you lyke the ſhomaker did euen now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Hertofore ſhulde ſuch one haue bene excommunicate, but nowe muſte we both heare and learne of the laye People<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> lyke the phariſees did of Chryſt, good katherin I pray the call Iohan our coke, he vſeth much to rede in the Byble, perchaunce he ſhall declare the ſcrypture better then I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he muſt ſeke me ſome ſentences out of the ſcripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Katheryn.</speaker>
               <p>Iohan Iohan / come to my maſter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohan.</speaker>
               <p>Honorable ſyr what is your pleaſure?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:23"/>
               <p> Our ſhomaker hath vexed me very lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and hath ſhewed me much<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out of the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, lyke the maner of the Lutherians is / ye muſte ſeke me oute ſome Chapter that I maye knowe yf he haue ſayde ryghte or no, that I myght conui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> hym <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The coke.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ought with ryght to knowe it your ſelfe, for you haue longe holpen to examine the anointed.</p>
               <p>To that we vſe but the doctrine of ſco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les / and that which hath bene written and made by men and very lyttel the ſpirytual lawe, which the holy fathers haue conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the councelles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The coke.</speaker>
               <p>It maketh no matter of that which the auncient fathers haue concluded in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell and what men (whiche are comme in afterward) haue written, when the ſame lawe doctrine and writtyng is not out of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> woorde and ſpirite of God. For the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes. Apoſtles and Euangelyſtes were men alſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Ergo they myght alſo erre, but the Lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theryans wyll not beleue it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:23"/>
               <speaker>The coke.</speaker>
               <p>No, for Peter ſayth. 2. Petri in the fyrſt <note place="margin">2. Petri. 1.</note> Chapter. That to prophet in the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate interpre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acion. For the ſcrypture came neuer by wyll of man, but holye men of God ſpake as they were moued by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he holygoſt. The falſe prophetes, which bryng many euell ſectes in that ſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fieth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en your ſpirituall eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, order, rule, and all the muincyons of men (without anye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rde of God) where with you daly go aboute.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>That is not ſpoken of vs, but of oure auncyent olde predeceſſours ano ſorego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The coke.</speaker>
               <p>O ye foles a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſlouth in harte to beleue <note place="margin">Luke. 24.</note> all that the prophetes haue ſpoken.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Katheryn.</speaker>
               <p>Harke Maſter, doth the cocke bydde you Crowe? ye wolde not ſuffer me to tell it you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>O thou lowſy vyllayn, wilt thou now teach me? thou arte alſo one of Luthers knaues, get the out of the dores, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d come no more into my houſe, thou vnſhamefaſt beaſt I cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell it the for beſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Shomaker.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:18301:24"/>
               <p> Ha ha ha / I perceaue it greueth yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet / that the ſhomaker hath ſtopt ſo well your mouth, left it not be ſo greate won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnto you, for God ſuffred (in the ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Teſtament) ſheapardes to declare hys worde, even ſo now muſt ye pharezees, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhauelynges be taught of ſhomakers and robblers / yea the very ſtones <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall call it in to your eares: fareye well ſyr domine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Katheryn.</speaker>
               <p>I maruayle that you can take the pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne to ſpeake to ſuch Rude beaſts, they ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther regarde you nor yet your holy oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall kepe me from him well inough, thow wycked and excommunycate kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue take hede of thy fyre / nowe I wyll go to the Church, and go you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the Market and buye vs a doſen of good quayles
/ for the chapleyn of my moſt reuerende Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the byſſhoppe ſhall dyne here wyth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re other gentlemen, we wyll kepe a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, now Carye the byble out of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and loke if the dyſe are in the tables<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and prouide vs of a fayre payre of cardes or two.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Katherin.</speaker>
               <p>It ſhalbe done, Syr, wyll ye come ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me
<pb facs="tcp:18301:24"/> anone after the proceſſion be done<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Parſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, loke the meate be ready.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Katheryn.</speaker>
               <p>yea forſothe Syr</p>
            </sp>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
